<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Android Event Capture App</title>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>The event capture Android app allows you capture, modify and list events. The event
      capture app works with event-based programs in DHIS 2, which handles anonymous events not
      linked to registered entities. These programs are suitable for handling scenarios such as
      facility surveys, hospital registry summaries and training events. However the app is not tied
      to any specific domain and can potentially be utilized for any scenario of event-based
      information.</para>
    <para>The event capture app allows you to capture events offline, i.e. without Internet
      connectivity. The app will automatically synchronize events with the online DHIS 2 server
      automatically when connectivity is present. This makes the app suitable for environments where
      Internet connectivity is scarce or unstable.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Installing and logging in</title>
    <para>The event capture add can be found on Google Play under the name "Event Capture for DHIS
      2".</para>
    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.hisp.dhis.android.eventcapture">Event Capture on Google Play</link></para>
    <para>You can download the APK file directly from the GitHub release page.</para>
    <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/dhis2/dhis2-android-eventcapture/releases">Event Capture GitHub releases</link></para>
    <para>Click on the app to open it after the installation is done. This will bring up the login
      screen.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Login screen.</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="35%" fileref="resources/images/android/ec/android-ec-login.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>In the <emphasis role="italic">URL</emphasis> field, enter the full URL to the DHIS 2
      instance (server) for which you want to capture and manage events for. Be careful to enter the
        <emphasis role="italic">http://</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic">https://</emphasis>
      part of the URL as well. In the <emphasis role="italic">username</emphasis> and <emphasis
        role="italic">password</emphasis> field, enter the username and password for your account at
      the given DHIS 2 instance. Note that you can use this login on the online DHIS 2 server as
      well, i.e. you will be using the same account as you will use when logging into DHIS 2 using a
      Web browser. After logging in the first time, the app will download meta-data from the online
      instance. This could take a few minutes so please be patient.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Viewing events</title>
    <para>The main screen will show an overview of events, as well as links to creating new ones.
      Start by selecting organisation unit and program from the selectors at the upper part of the
      screen.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Login screen.</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="35%" fileref="resources/images/android/ec/android-ec-event-list.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>The <emphasis role="italic">+</emphasis> button below the selectors will take you to the
      new event screen. Below this button, all events which have been registered for the selected
      organisation unit and program will be listed. Each column is configurable, and could show
      various types of information from each event. The column to the far right shows the
      synchronization status. <emphasis role="italic">Sent</emphasis> means that the event has been
      uploaded to the server, whereas <emphasis role="italic">Offline</emphasis> means that the
      event is so far only stored at your device. Events will be synchronized automatically once an
      Internet connection is present. You can swipe down on the screen in order to trigger a
      synchronization attempt.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Creating events</title>
    <para>Click on the <emphasis role="italic">+</emphasis> button to go to the new event form. The
      new event will be associated with the organisation unit and program you selected previously.
      The new event screen has a range of functions:</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Login screen.</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="35%" fileref="resources/images/android/ec/android-ec-new-event-top.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>The back button in the top top-left corner will take you back to the main screen (list of
      events). For programs that have specified sections, these sections will be displayed as a
      selector at the centre of the top bar. There are also right and left arrows which you can use
      to move between sections. You can use this selector and arrows to quickly navigate between
      form sections. The save button in the top-right corner will save what you have entered for the
      event so far. Data is also saved when you switch between sections.</para>
    <para>The <emphasis role="italic">Complete</emphasis> button on the second bar will mark the
      event as complete. The Validate button will trigger a check for validness of the information
      you have entered based on the validation rules which have been set up for the program.</para>
    <para>The first form field contains a date selector and indicators the time of when the event
      took place. The label is customizable and will vary from system to system. The <emphasis
        role="italic">Enter coordinates</emphasis> field, which will be displayed if the program is
      configured to store coordinates, lets you use the GPS capability of your device to set the
      longitude and latitude of your current location by pressing the circle-like symbol to its
      right. You can alternatively enter the coordinates directly.</para>
    <para>The event entry form itself will be rendered below. The type of input field selector will
      depend on the type of the data element representing the input field. For example, you will see
      date selectors, free text input and numeric input fields. Data elements with predefined
      options will be rendered using a special dialog where you can either click directly on options
      or use a text input field to search for a specific option (useful if there is a high number of
      options).</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Login screen.</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="35%" fileref="resources/images/android/ec/android-ec-option-set-selector.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Modifying events</title>
    <para>After an event has been created you can go back to or modify the event by simply clicking
      on it in the event list. This will open the event form pre-populated with information that has
      been captured so far.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Login screen.</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="35%" fileref="resources/images/android/ec/android-ec-event-form.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Settings</title>
    <para>The settings screen lets you do configure synchronization frequency and log out.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Login screen.</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="35%" fileref="resources/images/android/ec/android-ec-settings.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>The <emphasis role="italic">frequency of automatic synchronization attemps</emphasis> can
      be set form the drop-down, where options range from one minute to one day. This affects the
      battery usage and bandwith consumption. The default of one hour is a sensible choice.</para>
    <para>The <emphasis role="italic">log out</emphasis> button will log you out of the app, and
      request you to enter the login information again. You are not intended to log out of the
      application between each session. This is mostly useful when you want to log into another DHIS
      2 online instance.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
