<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Program rules</title>
  <para>This chapter covers how to configure and use program rules. Program rules provide a means to
    control dynamic behavior of the user interface in tracker and event capture. Program rules are
    based on expressions composed of data elements and attributes of tracked entities.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>The purpose of program rules is to provide a way to produce complex dynamic behaviors in
      tracker and event capture. The program rules enables the programs to respond to data values
      entered in a program. The behaviors that can be configured as of now is skip logic and
      validation rules. Program rules is consisting of one <emphasis role="bold"
        >expression</emphasis>, and one or more <emphasis role="bold">actions</emphasis> that is
      triggered in the user interface when the <emphasis role="bold">expression</emphasis> is true.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Setup</title>
    <para> Program rules can be managed from the &quot;Programs and Attributes&quot; app. Once in
      the app, navigate to Programs. A program rule belongs to exactly one program, so click on the
      program for which you want to manage rules and from the context menu navigate to &quot;View
      program rules&quot;. This will open the list of existing rules, if any, for this program. </para>
    <para> To <emphasis role="bold">add</emphasis> a rule, click the &quot;Add new&quot; button in
      the top right corner. This will open the new rule screen. Provide a name, short name, code,
      description, value type, expression and list of actions for the rule. </para>
    <para> To <emphasis role="bold">edit</emphasis> a rule, click on the relevant rule in the list
      to open the context menu and click &quot;Edit&quot;. This will open the edit rule screen,
      where you can modify the relevant values. </para>
    <para> To <emphasis role="bold">remove</emphasis> a rule, click on the relevant rule in the list
      to open the context menu and click &quot;Remove&quot;. Click &quot;OK&quot; in the
      confirmation dialog to remove the rule. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Program rule list with context menu</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/program_rules/program-rule-list.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Program rule anatomy</title>
    <para> During data entry, program rules <emphasis role="bold">expressions</emphasis> are
      evaluated each time the user interface is displayed, and each time a data element is changed.
      Most types of actions will take effect immediately as the user enters values in tracker or
      event capture. </para>
    <para> Each program rule is given a name and description (see section &quot;Program rule
      details&quot;). These fields are not shown to the end user, and are only meant for the program
      administrator. The active part of a program rule consists of an <emphasis role="bold"
        >expression</emphasis> (consult <xref linkend="program_rules_expressions"/> for details)
      more <emphasis role="bold">actions</emphasis>(see section <xref
        linkend="program_rules_defining_actions"/> for details) that will be performed if the
      expression is true. </para>
    <para>The expression is built from operators, user-defined static values and and <emphasis
        role="bold">source fields</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="program_dules_adding_source_fields"
      /> for details). The source fields represent attribute and data element values which will be
      evaluated as part of the expression. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Edit program rule user interface</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/program_rules/program-rule-edit.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title id="program_dules_adding_source_fields"> Adding source fields </title>
    <para> Source fields represent a uniform way to include data values and attribute values in
      expressions. The source fields is defined as needed when creating expressions . When creating
      your first expression, you will typically have to define one or more source fields first, as
      expressions usually contain at least one data element or attribute value to be meaningful. The
      source fields is shared between all rules in your program, and by creating several rules,
      these will share the same library of source fields. </para>
    <para> To add a source field, click the &quot;+ Add source field&quot; button under the source
      fields list. This will open the following dialog: </para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Add source field dialog</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="50%"
            fileref="resources/images/program_rules/program-rule-source-field.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold"> Source type:</emphasis> The source types is determining how the
            source field is populated with a value: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold"> Data element newest event program: </emphasis>Populates a
                  source field with the newest data value collected for one data element within the
                  enrollment. The newest data value is determined with event date. </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold"> Data element newest event program stage:</emphasis>
                  Populates a source field with the newest data value collected for one data element
                  within a specified program stage. In case of several events within the program
                  stage, the newest data value will be selected by event date. </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold"> Tracked entity attribute:</emphasis> Populates the source
                  field with a specified tracked entity attribute for the current enrollment. Note:
                  When selecting this option, fields for selecting program stage and data element is
                  hidden, and a field for selecting tracked entity attribute is displayed instead.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold"> Source program stage:</emphasis> In case of retrieving data value
            from a specific program stage, this field is used to define what program stage to
            retrieve data from. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold"> Source data element:</emphasis> Used to select which data element
            to retrieve data value for. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold"> Variable name</emphasis>: Specifying the name that is used for
            the source field when writing expressions. It is encouraged to use a name that makes the
            expressions readable. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="program_rules_expressions">
    <title> Defining expressions </title>
    <para> Each program rule has a single expression that determines whether rules action should be
      triggered, if the expression evaluates to true. If the expression is true the program rule is
      in effect and the actions will be executed. If the expression is false, the program rule is no
      longer in effect and the actions will no longer be applied. </para>
    <para> As a simple example, an expression is defined below using a single user-define static
      value, source fields(see previous chapter) and/or operators. Expressions can be typed into the
      edit expression text box, but buttons are available for inserting operators and source fields
      at the cursors position. To insert source fields, click the source field name within the list
      at the left. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Expression text box</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="50%"
            fileref="resources/images/program_rules/program-rule-expression.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para> The folliwng list provides a comprehensive list of operators which can be used to define
      an expression. <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">+</emphasis> Add numbers together </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">-</emphasis> Subtract numbers from each other </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis> Multiply two numbers </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">/</emphasis> Divide two numbers </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">%</emphasis> The modulus of two numbers </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">&amp;&amp;</emphasis> Logical AND. True only when the expression
            on the left and right side is true. The left and right side can be yes/no, yes only or a
            subexpression in parenthesis. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">||</emphasis> Logical OR. True when either the expression on the
            left or the expression on the right side is true. The left and right side can be yes/no,
            yes only or a subexpression in parenthesis. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">&gt;</emphasis> Left number greater than right number </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">&gt;=</emphasis> Left number greater than or equal to right number
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">&lt;</emphasis> Left number less than right number </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">&lt;=</emphasis> Left number less than or equal to right number
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">==</emphasis> Left side equal to right side. Supports numbers,
            text, yes/no and yes only. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">!=</emphasis> Left side not equal to right side. Supports numbers,
            text, yes/no and yes only. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">!</emphasis> Negates the following value. Can be used for yes/no,
            yes only or a subexpression in parenthesis. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">()</emphasis> Parenthesis is used to group subexpressions. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist> In addition to the standard mathematical operators, a number of custom
      functions are also available. </para>
    <para>
      <table frame="all">
        <title>Functions</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="newCol2" colwidth="2*"/>
          <colspec colnum="3" colname="c2" colwidth="3.61*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Function</entry>
              <entry>Arguments</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:ceil</entry>
              <entry>(number)</entry>
              <entry>Rounds the input argument <emphasis role="bold">up</emphasis> to the nearest
                whole number. <para> Example: <screen>d2:ceil(#{hemoglobinValue})</screen>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:floor</entry>
              <entry>(number)</entry>
              <entry>Rounds the input argument <emphasis role="bold">down</emphasis> to the nearest
                whole number. <para> An example producing the number of weeks the woman is pregnant.
                  Notice that the subexpression #{gestationalAgeDays}/7 is evaluated before the
                  floor function is executed: <screen>d2:floor(#{gestationalAgeDays}/7)</screen>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:round</entry>
              <entry>(number)</entry>
              <entry>Rounds the input argument to the nearest whole number.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:modulus</entry>
              <entry>(number,number)</entry>
              <entry>Produces the modulus when dividing the first with the second argument. <para>
                  An example producing the number of days the woman is into her current pregnancy
                  week: <screen>d2:modulus(#{gestationalAgeDays},7)</screen>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:zing</entry>
              <entry>(number)</entry>
              <entry>Evaluates the argument of type number to zero if the value is negative,
                otherwise to the value itself.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:oizp</entry>
              <entry>(number)</entry>
              <entry>Evaluates the argument of type number to one if the value is zero or positive,
                otherwise to zero. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:concatenate</entry>
              <entry>(object, [,object, object,...])</entry>
              <entry>Produces a string concatenated string from the input parameters. Supports any
                number of parameters. Will mainly be in use in future action types, for example to
                display gestational age with
                d2:concatenate(&apos;weeks&apos;,&apos;+&apos;,&apos;gestationalageDays&apos;).
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:daysBetween</entry>
              <entry>(date, date)</entry>
              <entry>Produces the number of days between the first and second argument. If the
                second argument date is before the first argument the return value will be the
                negative number of days between the two dates. The static date format is
                &apos;yyyy-MM-dd&apos;. <para> Example, calculating the gestational age(in days) of
                  a woman, based on the last menstrual period and the current event date:
                  <screen>d2:daysBetween(#{lastMenstrualDate},V{event_date})</screen>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:weeksBetween</entry>
              <entry>(date, date)</entry>
              <entry>Produces the number of full weeks between the first and second argument. If the
                second argument date is before the first argument the return value will be the
                negative number of weeks between the two dates. The static date format is
                &apos;yyyy-MM-dd&apos;.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:monthsBetween</entry>
              <entry>(date, date)</entry>
              <entry>Produces the number of full months between the first and second argument. If
                the second argument date is before the first argument the return value will be the
                negative number of months between the two dates. The static date format is
                &apos;yyyy-MM-dd&apos;.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:yearsBetween</entry>
              <entry>(date, date)</entry>
              <entry>Produces the number of years between the first and second argument. If the
                second argument date is before the first argument the return value will be the
                negative number of years between the two dates. The static date format is
                &apos;yyyy-MM-dd&apos;.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:addDays</entry>
              <entry>(date, number)</entry>
              <entry>Produces a date based on the first argument date, adding the second argument
                number of days. <para> An example calculating the pregnancy due date based on the
                  last menstrual period: <screen>d2:addDays(#{lastMenstrualDate},283)</screen>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:count</entry>
              <entry>(sourcefield)</entry>
              <entry>Counts the number of values that is entered for the source field in the
                argument. The source field parameter is the name of one of the defined source fields
                in the program - see example <para> Example usage where #{previousPregnancyOutcome}
                  is one of the source fields in a repeatable program stage &quot;previous
                  pregnancy&quot;: <screen>d2:count(&apos;previousPregnancyOutcome&apos;)</screen>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:countIfValue</entry>
              <entry>(sourcefield,text)</entry>
              <entry>Counts the number of matching values that is entered for the source field in
                the first argument. Only occurrences that matches the second argument is counted.
                The source field parameter is the name of one of the defined source fields in the
                program - see example. <para> Example usage where #{previousPregnancyOutcome} is one
                  of the source fields in a repeatable program stage &quot;previous pregnancy&quot;.
                  The following function will produce the number of previous pregnancies that ended
                  with abortion:
                  <screen>d2:countIfValue(&apos;previousPregnancyOutcome&apos;,&apos;Abortion&apos;)
                                    </screen>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:countIfZeroPos</entry>
              <entry>(sourcefield)</entry>
              <entry>Counts the number of values that is zero or positive entered for the source
                field in the argument. The source field parameter is the name of one of the defined
                source fields in the program - see example. <para> Example usage where
                  #{fundalHeightDiscrepancy} is one of the source fields in program, and it can be
                  either positive or negative. The following function will produce the number of
                  positive occurrences:
                  <screen>d2:countIfZeroPos(&apos;fundalHeightDiscrepancy&apos;)
                                    </screen>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:hasValue</entry>
              <entry>(sourcefield)</entry>
              <entry>Evaluates to true of the argument source field contains a value, false if no
                value is entered. <para> Example usage, to find if the source field
                  #{currentPregnancyOutcome} is yet filled in:
                  <screen>d2:hasValue(&apos;currentPregnancyOutcome&apos;)
                                    </screen>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:zpvc</entry>
              <entry>(object, [,object, object,...])</entry>
              <entry>Returns the number of numeric zero and positive values among the given object
                arguments. Can be provided with any number of arguments.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:validatePattern</entry>
              <entry>(text, regex-pattern)</entry>
              <entry>Evaluates to true if the input text is an exact match with the supplied
                regular expression pattern. The regular expression needs to be escaped.<para> Example:
                <screen>d2:validatePattern(A{nrc},'\\d{6}\/\\d{2}\/\\d')</screen></para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:left</entry>
              <entry>(text, num-chars)</entry>
              <entry>Evaluates to the left part of a text, num-chars from the first character.
                  <para> The text can be quoted or evaluated from a variable:
                  <screen>d2:left(#{variableWithText}, 3)</screen></para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:right</entry>
              <entry>(text, num-chars)</entry>
              <entry>Evaluates to the right part of a text, num-chars from the last character.
                  <para> The text can be quoted or evaluated from a variable:
                  <screen>d2:right(#{variableWithText}, 2)</screen></para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:substring</entry>
              <entry>(text, start-char-num, end-char-num)</entry>
              <entry>Evaluates to the part of a string specified by the start and end character
                number. <para> The text can be quoted or evaluated from a variable:
                  <screen>d2:right(#{variableWithText}, 2, 4)</screen></para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:split</entry>
              <entry>(text, delimiter, element-num)</entry>
              <entry>Split the text by delimiter, and keep the nth element(0 is the first).<para>
                  The text can be quoted or evaluated from a variable, the delimiter must be quoted:
                  <screen>d2:split(#{variableWithText}, '-', 1)</screen></para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:length</entry>
              <entry>(text)</entry>
              <entry>Find the length of a string. <para> Example:
                  <screen>d2:length(#{variableWithText})</screen></para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para>Functions can be nested within each other and with subexpressions to form more complex
        conditions. An example that produces the gestational age in weeks, based on last menstrual
        date: </para>
      <screen>d2:floor( d2:daysBetween(#{lastMenstrualDate},V{event_date}) / 7 )</screen>
    </tip>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title id="program_rules_defining_actions"> Defining actions </title>
    <para> Each program rule has one or more actions attached. These are the behaviors that is
      triggered in the user interface when the expression(see previous chapter) is true. Actions
      will be applied at once if the expression is true, and will be reverted if the expression is
      no longer true. </para>
    <para> To add a new action, click the &quot;+ add action&quot; button at the bottom of the
      program rule page. Once actionshas been added, they can be removed again by clicking the -
      button at the right side of the actions row. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Expression text box</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="80%"
            fileref="resources/images/program_rules/program-rule-add-action.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para> There are several types of <emphasis role="bold">actions</emphasis>, and the type is
      selected individually for each action row. </para>
    <section>
      <title> Hide field action </title>
      <para> A <emphasis role="bold">hide field action</emphasis> is defined by selecting &quot;Hide
        field&quot; in the first column of the action row. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Hide field action</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%"
              fileref="resources/images/program_rules/program-rule-hide-field-action.png"
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para> The second column is optional, and it allows defining a custom message to the end user
        in case the rule hides and blanks out the field after the end user typed in or selected a
        value. </para>
      <para>If a hide field action hides a field that contains a value, the field will always
        removed. If no message is defined, a standard message will be displayed to alert the
        user</para>
      <para> The third column specifies which data element that the <emphasis role="bold">hide field
          action</emphasis> should hide. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title> Hide section action </title>
      <para> A hide field action is defined by selecting &quot;Hide section&quot; in the first
        column of the action row. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Expression text box</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%"
              fileref="resources/images/program_rules/program-rule-hide-section-action.png"
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para> The second column is optional, and it allows defining a custom message to the end user
        in case the rule hides a section that contains a field that again has a value. </para>
      <para> If a hide section action hides a section with one or more fields that contains a value,
        these fields will always be removed. If no message is defined, a standard message will be
        displayed to alert the user. </para>
      <para> The third column specifies which section that the hide section action should hide.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title> Show warning action </title>
      <para> A <emphasis role="bold">show warning action</emphasis> is defined by selecting
        &quot;show warning&quot; in the first column of the action row. A show warning action is
        used to give the user a warning about the data being entered, but at the same time allowing
        the user to save and continue. Warnings can be used to help the user avoid errors in the
        data entered, while at the same time allowing the user to consciously disregard it and save
        a value that is outside preset expectations. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Show warning action</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%"
              fileref="resources/images/program_rules/program-rule-show-warning-action.png"
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para> The second column is mandatory, and is used to define the message shown to the user
        when the expression is true and the action is triggered. </para>
      <para> The third column specifies which data element or attribute to link the warning to, and
        is meant to be a recommendation to the user regarding where the cause of the warning can be
        rectified. In case several data elements or attributes are involved, when defining the rule,
        you should choose the one that is most likely that the user would need to consider. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title> Show error action </title>
      <para> A <emphasis role="bold">show error action</emphasis> is defined by selecting &quot;show
        error&quot; in the first column of the action row. A show error action is used whenever
        there are rules which must strictly be adhered to. The show error action prevents the user
        from continuing until the error is resolved. Such a strict validation should only be used
        whenever it is certain that the evaluated expression is never true unless the user has made
        a mistake in data entry. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Show error action</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%"
              fileref="resources/images/program_rules/program-rule-show-error-action.png"
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para> The second column is mandatory, and is used to define the message shown to the user
        when the expression is true and the action is triggered. </para>
      <para> The third column specifies which data element or attribute to link the error to, and is
        meant to be a cue for the user regarding where the cause of the error can be rectified. In
        case several data elements or attributes is involved, choose the one that is most likely
        that the user would need to change. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
