<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Program Indicators</title>
  <para>This chapter covers how to configure and use program indicators.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>The purpose of program indicators is to provide a way to produce calculated values based
      on data elements and attributes. Program indicators contain an expression and a filter, which
      in combination determines how the indicator should be calculated.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Setup</title>
    <para>Program indicators can be managed from the "Programs and Attributes" app. Once in the app,
      navigate to Programs. A program indicator belongs to exactly one program, so click on the
      program for which you want to create an indicator and from the context menu navigate to "View
      program indicators". This will open the list of existing indicators, if any, for this
      program.</para>
    <para>To <emphasis role="bold">add</emphasis> an indicator, click the "Add new" button in the
      top right corner. This will open the new indicator screen. Provide a name, short name, code,
      description, value type, expression and filter for the indicator.</para>
    <para>To <emphasis role="bold">edit</emphasis> an indicator, click on the relevant indicator in
      the list to open the context menu and click "Edit". This will open the edit indicator screen,
      where you can modify the relevant values.</para>
    <para>To <emphasis role="bold">remove</emphasis> an  indicator, click on the relevant indicator
      in the list to open the context menu and click "Remove". Click "OK" in the confirmation dialog
      to remove the indicator.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Calculation</title>
    <para>Program indicators are calculated based on its expression and filter.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <para> </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
