<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "docbookV4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title id="dashboards">Dashboards</title>
  <para>Dashboards are intended to provide quick access to different analytical objects (maps, charts, reports, tables, etc) to an individual user. Dashboards can also be shared with user groups. For instance, a user or administrator could create a dashboard called &quot;Malaria&quot; which might contain all relevant information on malaria. This dashboard could then be shared with the user group called &quot;Malaria control&quot;, which might consist of all users of the malaria control programme. All users within this group would then be able to view the same dashboard.</para>
  <section id="dashboards_setup">
    <title>Setting up the dashboard</title>
    <para>The dashboard can contain any number of objects (charts, maps, reports, tables, resources, etc). These can be freely arranged on the dashboard as you wish.  Dashboard items can be located and added by searching for favourites, resources, users or messages in the available search box and clicking on the &quot;Add&quot; button. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="90%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dashboard/dashboard_overview.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>In this screen shot, the dashboard has already been populated with a number of objects, such as charts, map views, tables and messages. There are several hyperlink options available on each item: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Remove</para>
        <para>Allows you to remove the item from the dashboard when you have the appropriate user rights.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Get as Image</para>
        <para>Opens up a pop-up window and allows you to download the image to your computer.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Share interpretation</para>
        <para>Allows you to share an interpretation of the dashboard item. Your interpretation will be shared publicly with other users of the DHIS2 system, in the &quot;Interpretation&quot; section of the dashboard. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Explore</para>
        <para>Loads the favorite in its corresponding app (ie. a map will open full-sized in the GIS app).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Resize</para>
        <para>Resizes the dashboard item. There are 3 sizes in which to choose from. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Maps, charts and tables can be viewed as full size as images (in the case of charts and map views) or as HTML resources (in the case of reports, tables and messages). </para>
    <para>To reorder how the dashboard appears, simply drag-and-drop any of the objects to a new position. In order to change between the various dashboards which are available, simply select the listed items that are available to review. The list can be scrolled though by using the &lt;, &gt; symbols to the left of the dashboard names.  </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Managing the Dashboard</title>
    <para>In addition to adding items or modifying the layout of a dashboard, further options allow you to add additional dashboards, modify their names, delete an entire dashboard an share the dashboard with other users. These additional items can be managed using the &quot;Add,&quot; &quot;Manage,&quot; and &quot;Share&quot; links on the top left of the dashboard next to the dashboard names. </para>
    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Add</para>
          <para>Allows additional dashboards to be added.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Manage</para>
          <para>Can change the name of the dashboard, add messages to  or delete the dashboard. This applies to the currently selected dashboard item. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Share</para>
          <para>Allows the sharing of dashboard items with  user groups. User permissions can also be assigned to each user group.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Dashboard Sharing</title>
    <para>In order to share a dashboard with user groups, first select &quot;Share&quot; from the dashboard page. This will bring up the dashboard sharing settings options. To share the dashboard with specific user groups, type in their name in the sharing settings dialogue box and click on the &quot;+&quot; sign to add them to the dashboard sharing settings</para>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/dashboard/dashboard_sharing settings.png" align="center" format="PNG" scale="80"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>All dashboards have two sharing groups set by default.</para>
    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>External access (without login)</para>
          <para>This option, when selected, provides access to the dashboard as an external resource. This is useful for when you are creating an external web portal but would like to call information from a dashboard you have made internally within DHIS2. By default, this option is not selected. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Public access (with login)</para>
          <para>This option allows  the selected dashboard to be pushed to all users within your DHIS2 instance. This can also be hidden from public view by selecting the &quot;None&quot; option, which is the default option for new dashboards.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
    <para>User groups which have been added manually can be assigned two types of permissions within the dashboard</para>
    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Can view</para>
          <para>Provides the user group with view only rights to the dashboard.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Can edit and view</para>
          <para>Allows the user groups to edit the dashboard in addition to viewing it. Editing allows for altering the layout, resizing and removing items, renaming/deleting the dashboard etc. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title id="dashboard_messages">Messages and feedback</title>
    <para>DHIS2 has certain functions to facilitate communication between different users and user groups. This type of communication is important to facilitate feedback regarding data quality,  timeliness of submissions, or to simply answer a question which a particular user may have. </para>
    <para>Feedback messages are sent to a particular group of users and can be sent by all users who
      have access to the dashboard module. In order to enable the receipt of feedback messages sent
      from the dashboard, you must set the system setting &quot;Feedback recipients&quot; which is
      available from the Maintenance-&gt;System settings dialog. Be sure to define a user group
      (e.g. &quot;Feedback recipients&quot;) with all of the users who should receive feedback
      messages. Refer to the section in this manual on &quot;User groups&quot; for more information
      of how to do this. Once the &quot;Feedback recipients&quot; user group has been defined, each
      time a feedback message is sent, it will appear as a message in each of the &quot;Feedback
      recipients&quot; message queue within DHIS2. Note that messages will not be sent to users
      email addresses, but will only appear within the DHIS2 application. </para>
    <para>To send a new feedback message, simply select &quot;Write feedback&quot; from the dashboard. Provide a subject and text in the respective text boxes. The message will appear in all of the specified users message queue. </para>
    <para>Messages can be sent to either a specific user, user  group or groups of users who have been assigned to particular organisation units. To write a new message, simply click &quot;Messages&quot; from the dashboard screen and then press the &quot;Write message&quot; button.. Select an organisation unit (or group of organisation units) from the &quot;Recipients&quot; organisational unit tree. In the &quot;To user&quot; box you can select specific users or user groups. Provide a Subject and Text. To send the message, press the &quot;Send&quot; button. You can discard the message by pressing the &quot;Discard&quot; button as seen in the screenshot below.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="90%" align="center" scale="70" fileref="resources/images/dashboard/dashboard_message.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>To read messages which have been sent to you, select &quot;Messages&quot; from the &quot;Dashboard&quot; . You messages will be displayed as a list. Click the desired message to read all of the messages in this particular conversation. </para>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%" align="center" fileref="resources/images/dashboard/dashboard_messages_queue.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
</chapter>
