<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter>
  <title>Program Indicators</title>
  <para>This chapter covers how to configure and use program indicators. Program indicators in
    essence are expressions based on data elements and attributes of tracked entities.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>The purpose of program indicators is to provide a way to produce calculated values based
      on data elements and attributes. Program indicators have an aggregation type, an expression
      and a filter, which in combination determines how the indicator will be evaluated.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Setup</title>
    <para>Program indicators can be managed from the "Programs and Attributes" app. Once in the app,
      navigate to Programs. A program indicator belongs to exactly one program, so click on the
      program for which you want to create an indicator and from the context menu navigate to "View
      program indicators". This will open the list of existing indicators, if any, for this
      program.</para>
    <para>To <emphasis role="bold">add</emphasis> an indicator, click the "Add new" button in the
      top right corner. This will open the new indicator screen. Provide a name, short name, code,
      description, value type, expression and filter for the indicator.</para>
    <para>To <emphasis role="bold">edit</emphasis> an indicator, click on the relevant indicator in
      the list to open the context menu and click "Edit". This will open the edit indicator screen,
      where you can modify the relevant values.</para>
    <para>To <emphasis role="bold">remove</emphasis> an  indicator, click on the relevant indicator
      in the list to open the context menu and click "Remove". Click "OK" in the confirmation dialog
      to remove the indicator.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Program indicator list with context menu</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/program_indicator/program-indicator-list.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Indicator evaluation</title>
    <para>Program indicators are evaluated based on its aggregation type, expression and filter. The
      order of evaluation is as follows:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis role="italic">filter</emphasis> will filter the events which become part
          of the evaluation / aggregation routine.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis role="italic">expression</emphasis> will be evaluated per event.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>All evaluated expression values will be <emphasis role="italic">aggregated</emphasis>
          according to the aggregation type of the program indicator.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section>
      <title>Aggregation type</title>
    <para>The aggregation type determines how the program indicator
        will be aggregated. The following aggregation types are available:</para>
      <para>average, sum, count, std dev, variance, min, max, custom (allows inline aggregation
        types in expression)</para>
      <para>The custom aggregation type is special as it allows you to specify the aggregation type
        inline in the expression. All other aggregation types are applied to the entire
        expression.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Expression</title>
    <para>The expression defines how the indicator is being calculated. The expression can contain
        references to various entities which will be substituted with a related values when the
        indicator is calculated:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Data elements: Will be substituted with the value of the data element for the time
              period and organisation unit for which the calculation is done. Refers to both program
              stage and data element.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Attributes: Will be substituted with the value of the attribute for the person /
              tracked entity for which the calculation is done.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Variables: Will be substituted with special values linked to the program,
              including incident date and date of enrollment for the person, current date and count
              of values in the expression for the time period and organisation unit for which the
              calculation is done.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Constants: Will be substituted with the value of the constant.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    <para>The expression is a mathematical expression that can contain operators which include
      multiply, divide, plus and minus. The expression will be evaluated <emphasis role="italic">per
        event</emphasis>, then aggregated according to its aggregation type.</para>    
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Program indicator list with context menu</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/program_indicator/program-indicator-expression.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>An example expression that includes both attributes, data elements and constants looks like
      this:<screen>(A{GPkGfbmArby} + #{mCXR7u4kNBW.NFkjsNiQ9PH}) * C{bCqvfPR02Im}</screen></para>
    <para>An example expression which uses the custom aggregation type and hence can use inline
      aggregation types looks like
      this:<screen>(sum(#{mCXR7u4kNBW.K0A4BauXJDl} * #{mCXR7u4kNBW.NFkjsNiQ9PH}) / sum(#{mCXR7u4kNBW.NFkjsNiQ9PH})) * 100</screen></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Filter</title>
    <para>The filter is applied to events and filters the data
      source used for the calculation of the indicator. I.e. the filter is applied to the set of
      events before the indicator expression is being evaluated. The filter must evaluate to either
      true or false. It filter is applied to each individual event. If the filter evaluates to true
      then the event is included later in the expression evaluation, if not it is ignored. The
      filter can, in a similar way as expressions, contain references to data elements, attributes
      and constants.</para>
      <para>The indicator filter can in addition use logical operators including the
        following:</para>
      <table frame="all">
        <title>Operators</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="5.11*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Operator</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>and</entry>
              <entry>Logical AND</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>or</entry>
              <entry>Logical OR</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>==</entry>
              <entry>Equal to</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>!=</entry>
              <entry>Not equal to</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>&lt;</entry>
              <entry>Less than</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>&lt;=</entry>
              <entry>Less than or equal to</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>></entry>
              <entry>Greater than</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>>=</entry>
              <entry>Greater than or equal to</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>These operators can be used to form logical expressions which ultimately evaluates to
        true or false. E.g. one can express that multiple data elements must be a specific value, or
        that specific attributes must have numerical values less or greater than a constant.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Program indicator list with context menu</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="resources/images/program_indicator/program-indicator-filter.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>You can switch between data elements, attributes, variables and constants by using the
      tabs. You can include such items into expressions and filters by double-clicking in the list.
      The buttons below the expression area can be used to insert operators.</para>
    <para>An example filter that uses both attributes and data elements looks like
      this:<screen>A{cejWyOfXge6} == 'Female' and #{A03MvHHogjR.a3kGcGDCuk6} &lt;= 2</screen></para>    
    <para><emphasis role="italic">A tip to expert users:</emphasis> DHIS 2 is using the JEXL library
      for evaluating expressions which supports additional syntax beyond what is covered in this
      documentation. See the reference at the <ulink
        url="http://commons.apache.org/proper/commons-jexl/reference/syntax.html">project home
        page</ulink> to learn how you can create more sophisticated expressions.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Functions</title>
      <para>The indicator expression and filter support a range of functions. The functions can be
        applied to data elements and attributes:</para>
      <table frame="all">
        <title>Functions</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.23*"/>
          <colspec colname="newCol2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="3" colwidth="5.33*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Function</entry>
              <entry>Arguments</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:daysBetween</entry>
              <entry>(date, date)</entry>
              <entry>Produces the number of days between two data elements/attributes of type
                date.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:zing</entry>
              <entry>(number)</entry>
              <entry>Evaluates the data element/attribute of type number to zero if the value is
                negative, otherwise to the value itself.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>d2:oizp</entry>
              <entry>(number)</entry>
              <entry>Evaluates the data element/attribute of type number to one if the value is zero
                or positive, otherwise to zero. </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>An example expression that uses functions looks like
        this:<screen>d2:zing(A{GPkGfbmArby}) + d2:oizp(#{mCXR7u4kNBW.NFkjsNiQ9PH}))</screen></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Variables</title>
      <para>The indicator expression and filter support a range of variables:</para>
      <table frame="all">
        <title>Variables</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="3.55*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Variable</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>execution_date</entry>
              <entry>The date of when the event took place.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>current_date</entry>
              <entry>The current date.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>value_count</entry>
              <entry>The number of non-null values in the expression part of the event.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>zero_pos_value_count</entry>
              <entry>The number of numeric positive values in the expression part of the
                event.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>An example expression that uses variables looks like
        this:<screen>(#{A03MvHHogjR.a3kGcGDCuk6} + #{A03MvHHogjR.wQLfBvPrXqq}) / V{value_count}</screen></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
