<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Getting started with DHIS 2 as end-user</title>
  <section>
    <title>Getting started with DHIS 2</title>
    <para>After reading this chapter you will be able to understand:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>How to open the DHIS 2</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>How to  log in and out of the application</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>How to navigate the application and access its features</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Opening DHIS 2</title>
    <para>The DHIS 2 is a web-based application and will be available in an Internet  browser when you have Internet connection.</para>
    <para>Open a browser, we recommend Google Chrome (download installer here: http://www.google.com/chrome) and in the address field you type in the URL of the DHIS 2 (ask your technical support team for this).</para>
    <para>You will then see the login screen of DHIS 2.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Logging in and out of the application</title>
    <para>Once you can see the blue login screen of DHIS 2 you must enter your user name and password to log in to the application. If the login is not successful you will be notified that the username or password is incorrect and asked to re-enter these credentials. Once you have successfully logged in you will see the DHIS Dashboard where you can immediately monitor the latest data in your selected charts and access your favourite DHIS sites (reports, maps etc).</para>
    <para>When you have finished your DHIS 2 session we recommend that you log out before closing the browser. Use the log out link in the upper right corner and you will be returned to the log in screen.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <title>Login screen</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/getting_started/login.png" format="PNG" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Navigating the application</title>
    <para>The DHIS 2 has two menu systems; the top menu, which houses areas for apps and the user profile, and the left side menu inside most modules to navigate between features inside each module.</para>
    <para>The DHIS 2 symbol in the top left corner is a fast link to the user-defined start page, the home page. Often this is set to the dashboard module.</para>
    <section>
      <title>The top menu - access to the modules</title>
      <para>DHIS 2 consists of various apps (major components) which each have specific features, such as data entry, reporting, dashboard. You can access these  from the top menu  under Apps. Under profile, details relating to your user account, general user settings and information about DHIS 2 can be found.</para>
      <para>To move to a new app you need to move the mouse pointer to one of the top menu items, Apps or Profile, a sub-menu with additional items will then appear. Click on the item you would like to open.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Navigation inside modules</title>
      <para>When you open most of the  apps you will see the app main page which lists the major  features in the middle of the screen with a short description. Simply click on the feature you would like to open. </para>
      <para>When inside an app you will always see the left side menu with links to its features. Use this menu to jump between features. This is particular useful for navigation within the app. </para>
      <para>The data entry and dashboard modules do not have a menu system as they only contain one feature, everything is in one page, so there is no need for a menu there. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <title>Menu system</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/Reports_menu system.png" format="PNG" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
