<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Getting started with DHIS2 as end-user</title>
  <section>
    <title>Getting started with DHIS2</title>
    <para>After reading this chapter you will be able to understand:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>How to open the DHIS2</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>How to  log in and out of the application</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>How to navigate the application and access its features</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Opening DHIS2</title>
    <para>The DHIS2 is a web-based application and will be available in an Internet  browser when you have Internet connection.</para>
    <para>Open a browser, we recommend Google Chrome (download installer here: http://www.google.com/chrome) and in the address field you type hiskenya.org</para>
    <para>You will then see the login screen of DHIS2.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Logging in and out of the application</title>
    <para>Once you can see the blue login screen of DHIS2 you must enter your user name and password to log in to the application. If the login is not successful you will be notified that the username or password is incorrect and asked to re-enter these credentials. Once you have successfully logged in you will see the DHIS2 Dashboard where you can immediately monitor the latest data in your selected charts and access your favourite DHIS2 sites (reports, maps etc).</para>
    <para>When you have finished your DHIS2 session we recommend that you log out before closing the browser. Use the log out link in the upper right corner and you will be returned to the log in screen.</para>
    <screenshot>
      <title>Login screen</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/login_screen.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Navigating the application</title>
    <para>The DHIS2 has two menu systems; the top menu which leads to the various modules, and the left side menu inside most modules to navigate between features inside each module.</para>
    <para>The DHIS2 symbol in the top left corner is a fast link to the user-defined start page, the home page. Often this is set to the dashboard module.</para>
    <para>The logout button is on the far right of the top menu.</para>
    <section>
      <title>The top menu - access to the modules</title>
      <para>The DHIS2 consists of various modules (major components) which each have specific features, such as data entry, reporting, dashboard. You can access these modules from the top menu either under Maintenance or Services. Maintenance is mostly used by system administrators that maintain the application and might not be visible. Services is where you will find the more operational features like data entry, data quality and reporting. Under the top menu item Help you can access the built-in user manual, update your user details, or view information about the running DHIS2 application.</para>
      <para>To move to a new module you need to move the mouse pointer to one of the top menu items; Maintenance, Services, or Help. Then a submenu with modules will appear. Click on the module you would like to open.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Navigation inside modules</title>
      <para>When you open most of the  modules you will see the module main page which lists the major submodules or features in the middle of the screen with a short description. Simply click on the feature you would like to open.</para>
      <para>When inside a module you will always see the left side menu with links to its features. Use this menu to jump between features.</para>
      <para>The data entry and dashboard modules do not have a menu system as they only contain one feature, everything is in one page, so no need for a menu there. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <title>Menu system</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="100%" fileref="resources/images/dhis2UserManual/menu_system.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
