<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Using the Data
    <?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160421T142956+0200" comment="Review all graphics before commit to master"?>Visualizer<?oxy_comment_end?>
    app</title>
  <section xml:id="dvIntro">
    <title>Data Visualizer
      <?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160422T124514+0200" comment="Same concept information as in Pivot table app doc?"?>overview<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
    <screenshot>
      <info><title>Data visualizer module displaying a column chart.</title></info>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%" align="center"
            fileref="resources/images/visualizer/column_chart.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>With the
      D<?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160421T133120+0200" comment="Which type of data? What&apos;s the difference to the Event Visualizer?"?>ata<?oxy_comment_end?>
      Visualizer app, you can create dynamic data analysis and visualizations through charts and
      <?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160421T135116+0200" comment="What is a data table in this context?"?>data
      tables<?oxy_comment_end?>. You can freely select content, for example indicators, data
      elements, periods and organisation units, for an analysis. The app works well over poor
      Internet connections and generates charts in the web browser. Little data is transferred over
      the Internet.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Create a chart</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the <emphasis role="bold">Apps</emphasis> menu, click <emphasis role="bold">Data
            Visualizer</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select a chart type.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the menu to the left, select the
          <?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160421T142756+0200" comment="Correct term = data dimension?"?>dimension<?oxy_comment_end?>
          items you want to analyse, for
          example<?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160421T140324+0200" comment="Do these terms cover all possible selections?"?>
          data elements or indicators.<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Layout</emphasis> and
          <?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160421T143134+0200" comment="Is this correct for a chart?"?>arrange
          the
          <?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160421T142829+0200" comment="Correct term = data dimension item?
Or data dimension?
Or dimension?" mid="7"?>dimensions<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="7"?>
          .</para>
        <para>You can keep the default selection if you want.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Update</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>You can display a chart
      based on your selections simply by clicking the &quot;Update&quot; button on the top centre
      menu. This requires that you have selected one or more elements from all of the three
      dimensions - data (indicators, data elements, reporting rates), periods (relative, fixed) and
      organisation units (units or groups). Note that &quot;Last 12 Months&quot; from the period
      dimension and the root organisation unit are selected by default.</para>
    <para>Notice that you can hide and show individual data series in the chart by clicking directly
      on the series label in the chart - they appear either at the top or to the right of the
      chart.</para>
    <para>If you want to give the chart more space on your screen you can click on the triple
      left-arrow button on the top centre menu. This will collapse the left side menu. You can get
      this menu back by clicking on the same button again.<?oxy_custom_end?></para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dvChartTypes">
    <title>Select a chart type</title>
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Data Visualizer</emphasis> app has nine different chart types,
      each with different characteristics. To select a chart type:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>In <emphasis role="bold">Chart type</emphasis>, click the chart type you need.</para>
        <table frame="all">
          <title>Chart types</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.03*"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Chart type</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Description</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Column chart</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Displays information as vertical rectangular columns with lengths
                    proportional to the values they represent.</para>
                  <para>Useful when you want to, for example, compare performance of different
                    districts.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Stacked column chart</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Displays information as vertical rectangular columns, where bars
                    representing multiple categories are stacked on top of each other.</para>
                  <para>Useful when you want to, for example, display trends or sums of related data
                    elements.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Bar chart</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Same as column chart, only with horizontal bars.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Stacked bar chart</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Same as stacked column chart, only with horizontal bars.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Line chart</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Displays information as a series of points connected by straight lines. Also
                    referred to as time series.</para>
                  <para>Useful when you want to, for example, visualize trends in indicator data
                    over multiple time periods.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Area chart</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Is based on line chart, with the space between the axis and the line filled
                    with colors and the lines stacked on top of each other.</para>
                  <para>Useful when you want to compare the trends of related indicators.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Pie chart</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Circular chart divided into sectors (or slices).</para>
                  <para>Useful when you want to, for example, visualize the proportion of data for
                    individual data elements compared to the total sum of all data elements in the
                    chart.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Radar chart</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Displays
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160421T142149+0200" comment="What does this mean?"?>multivariate<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    data on axes starting from the same point. Also known as spider chart.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Speedometer chart</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para> Semi-circle chart which displays values out of 100 %. Also referred to as a
                    gauge chart. </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Update</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Select dimension items</title>
    <section xml:id="dvSeriesCategoryFilter">
      <?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160422T124651+0200" comment="Don&apos;t you have to select dimensions first before you can do this?

Compare to pivot tables."?>
      <title>Select series, category and filter</title>
      <?oxy_comment_end?>
      <para>The series, category and filter can be defined by selecting the &quot;Layout&quot;
        option in the data visualizer app. </para>
      <para>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="80%" align="center" scale="100"
                fileref="resources/images/visualizer/chart_layout.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </para>
      <para>This section lets you define which dimension of the data you want to appear as series,
        category and filter by dragging and dropping these options to the appropriate space. Only
        one dimension can be in each section. </para>
      <para>This asks for a closer explanation. Dimension in this regard refers to the elements
        which describe the data values in the system. We have three main dimensions in the
        system:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data: Includes data elements, indicators and datasets (reporting rates), describing
            the phenomena or event of the data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Periods: Describes when the event took place.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Organisation units: Describes where the event took place.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>The visualization module lets you use these dimensions completely flexible in terms of
        appearing as series, categories and filter. Understanding these concepts is most easily done
        by looking at the screenshot from the opening page below: </para>
      <screenshot>
        <info><title>Example chart illustrating the concepts of series, categories and
          filter.</title></info>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="80%" align="center"
              fileref="resources/images/visualizer/series_category_filter.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>More formally this can be described as following:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Series: A series is a set of continuous, related elements (for example periods or
            data elements) which you want to visualize in order to emphasize trends or relations in
            its data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Categories: A category is a set of elements (for example indicators or organisation
            units) for which you want to compare its data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Filter: Since most charts are two-dimensional, a filter must be used on the third
            dimension in order to use only a single element for the chart to become
            meaningful.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Select indicators and data elements</title>
      <para>The Data Visualizer app can display any number of indicators and data elements in a
        chart and data table. </para>
      <para>You can select both indicators and data elements to appear together in the same chart,
        with their order of appearance the same as the order in which they are selected. </para>
      <para>You can select indicators by choosing Indicators from the &quot;Data&quot; header and
        selecting an indicator group from the list of groups below it. This will make the indicators
        in the selected group appear in the list under &quot;Available indicators&quot; to the left.
        From that list you can double click on any indicator in order to select it, this will move
        it to the list under &quot;Selected indicators&quot;. Alternatively you can mark one or more
        indicators and click the single-arrow button. To select all indicators you simply click on
        the double-arrow button. To deselect indicators you can do correspondingly in the
        &quot;Selected indicators&quot; list.</para>
      <para>To select data elements choose Data Elements from the &quot;Data&quot; header. The same
        principle for selecting and deselecting indicators applies for data elements.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Select reporting rates</title>
      <para>The visualizer can display reporting rates in a chart, by itself or together with
        indicators and data elements. Reporting rates can be selected by choosing Reporting Rates
        from the &quot;Data&quot; header. Reporting rates are defined by data sets. It can be
        selected by double-clicking in the list of available data sets to the left.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Select fixed and relative periods</title>
      <para>Click on the &quot;Periods&quot; header. For fixed periods, select a period type from
        the combo box. You can select any number of fixed periods from any period type. Below the
        fixed period you will find the relative period checkboxes and you may select as many as you
        like. The names should be fairly self-descriptive and they are relative to the current date,
        meaning that if the current month is March and you select &quot;Last month&quot;, the month
        of February will be included in the chart. You are also free to combine fixed periods and
        relative periods in the same chart. Overlapping periods will be filtered so that they only
        appear once.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Select organisation units</title>
      <para>You can select which organisation units to include in the chart by clicking the
        &quot;Organisation units&quot; header. </para>
      <para>This section features three ways of selecting organisation units, which can be selected
        by clicking on the gear icon directly below the organisation units header. </para>
      <para>The default mode is called &quot;Organisation units&quot; and lets you select the
        organisation units you want to appear in the chart from the tree. This mode also features
        three checkboxes. Checking &quot;User org unit&quot; will disable the organisation unit tree
        and give you the organisation unit that is related to the current/logged in user instead.
        This is also useful for administrators as they can create a meaningful &quot;system&quot;
        favorite with this option checked and all users will find their respective organisation unit
        when they open it. The the same concept goes for &quot;User sub-units&quot; and &quot;User
        sub-x2-units&quot;. </para>
      <para>The second mode is called &quot;Select levels&quot;. Here you can select all
        organisation units at one or more levels. However, at the same time you also have the option
        to select parent organisation units in the tree, which makes it easy to select e.g. all
        facilities inside one or more districts. </para>
      <para>The same thing goes for the third mode called &quot;Select groups&quot;. Here you can
        select all organisation units inside one or more groups and parent organisation units at the
        same time.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Select organisation unit group sets and data element group sets</title>
      <para>Dimension tabs listed below &quot;Organisation units&quot; are organisation unit group
        sets and data element group sets. You are free to add groups from any of these group sets to
        your chart. Remember to add the group set in either the series, category or filters
        combobox.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Select additional data dimensions</title>
      <para>Following the organisation unit group sets and data element group sets additional data
        dimensions which have been configured to be used in analysis are found. Here you can add
        dimensions such as age, sex, etc. without having to add them in as detailed data element
        selections. This is useful when you want to separate these categories in your analysis.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Modify chart layout/Arrange dimensions</title>
    <para/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Change the display of your chart</title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="50%" align="center" scale="100"
            fileref="resources/images/visualizer/chart_options.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Options</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Set the options as required.</para>
        <table frame="all">
          <title>Chart options</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.5*"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Option</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Show values</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Shows the values above the series in the chart.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Hide empty category items</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Hides the category items with no data from the chart.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Show trend lines</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Displays the trend line which visualizes how your data evolves over time.
                    For example if performance is improving or deteriorating. Useful when periods
                    are selected as category. </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Target value /
                      <?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160422T121457+0200" comment="Suggest to dev to remove &quot;:&quot; in UI."?>title<?oxy_comment_end?>:</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Displays a horizontal line at the given domain value. Useful for example
                    when you want to compare your performance to the current target.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Base value / title:</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Displays a horizontal line at the given domain value. Useful for example
                    when you want to visualize how your performance has evolved since the beginning
                    of a process.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Sort order:</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Allows you to sort the values on your chart from either low to high or high
                    to low. </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Aggregation type:</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Defines how the data elements or indicators will be aggregated within the
                    chart. Some of the aggregation types are <emphasis role="bold">By data
                      element</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Count</emphasis>, <emphasis
                      role="bold">Min</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Max</emphasis>.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Include only completed events</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Includes only completed events in the aggregation process. This is useful
                    when you want for example to exclude partial events in indicator
                    calculations.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Range axis min/max:</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Defines the maximum and minium value which will be visible on the range
                    axis.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Range axis tick steps:</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Defines the number of ticks which will be visible on the range axis.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Range axis decimals:</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Defines the number of decimals which will be used for range axis
                    values.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Range axis title:</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Type a title here to display a label next to the range axis (also referred
                    to as the Y axis). Useful when you want to give context information to the
                    chart, for example about the unit of measure.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Domain axis title:</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para> Type a title here to display a label below the domain axis (also referred
                    to as the X axis). Useful when you want to give context information to the
                    chart, for example about the period type.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Hide chart legend</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Hides the legend and leaves more room for the chart itself.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Hide chart title</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Hides the title of your chart.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Chart title:</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Type any title here to display a it above the chart.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Update</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dvDisplayChart">
    <title>Display a chart</title>
    <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="166,89,220"?>
    <para>You can display a chart based on your selections simply by clicking the &quot;Update&quot;
      button on the top centre menu. This requires that you have selected one or more elements from
      all of the three dimensions - data (indicators, data elements, reporting rates), periods
      (relative, fixed) and organisation units (units or groups). Note that &quot;Last 12
      Months&quot; from the period dimension and the root organisation unit are selected by
      default.</para>
    <para>Notice that you can hide and show individual data series in the chart by clicking directly
      on the series label in the chart - they appear either at the top or to the right of the
      chart.</para>
    <para>If you want to give the chart more space on your screen you can click on the triple
      left-arrow button on the top centre menu. This will collapse the left side menu. You can get
      this menu back by clicking on the same button again.<?oxy_custom_end?></para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dvSaveChart">
    <title>Download a chart as an image or a PDF</title>
    <para>After you have created a chart you can download it to your local computer as an image or
      PDF file.</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Download</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Under <emphasis role="bold">Graphics</emphasis>, click <emphasis role="bold">Image
            (.png)</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">PDF (.pdf)</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>The file is automatically downloaded to your computer. Now you can for example embed
          the image file into a text document as part of a report. </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Download chart data source</title>
    <para>You can download the data source behind a chart in JSON, XML, Excel, CSV, JXRML or Raw
      data SQL formats with different identification schemes (ID, Code, and Name). The data document
      uses identifiers of the dimension items and opens in a new browser window to display the URL
      of the request to the Web API in the address bar. This is useful for developers of apps and
      other client modules based on the DHIS 2 Web API or for those who require a plan data source,
      for instance for import into statistical packages.</para>
    <para>To download plain data source formats:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Download</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Under <emphasis role="bold">Plain data source</emphasis>, click the format you want to
          download.</para>
        <para>
          <table frame="all">
            <title>Available formats</title>
            <tgroup cols="3">
              <colspec colname="newCol1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
              <colspec colname="c1" colnum="2" colwidth="1.83*"/>
              <colspec colname="c2" colnum="3" colwidth="2.6*"/>
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Format</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Action</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Description</para>
                  </entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>
                    <para>JSON</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">JSON</emphasis></para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Downloads JSON format based on ID property. </para>
                    <para>You can also download JSON format based on <emphasis role="bold"
                        >Code</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis> property. </para>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>
                    <para>XML</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">XML</emphasis></para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Downloads XML format based on ID property.</para>
                    <para>You can also download XML format based on <emphasis role="bold"
                        >Code</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis> property. </para>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Microsoft Excel</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Microsoft Excel</emphasis></para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Downloads XML format based on ID property.</para>
                    <para>You can also download Microsoft Excel format based on <emphasis
                        role="bold">Code</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>
                      property.</para>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>
                    <para>CSV</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>Click <emphasis role="bold">CSV</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Downloads CSV format based on ID property.</para>
                    <para>You can also download CSV format based on <emphasis role="bold"
                        >Code</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis> property.</para>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>
                    <para>JRXML</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Put the cursor on <emphasis role="bold">Advanced</emphasis> and click
                        <emphasis role="bold">JRXML</emphasis></para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Produces a template of a Jasper Report which can be further customized
                      based on your exact needs and used as the basis for a standard report in DHIS
                      2.</para>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Raw data SQL</para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Put the cursor on <emphasis role="bold">Advanced</emphasis> and click
                        <emphasis role="bold">Raw data SQL</emphasis></para>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <para>Provides the actual SQL statement used to generate the data visualization.
                      You can use it as a data source in a Jasper report, or as the basis for a SQL
                      view.</para>
                  </entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dvFavorites">
    <title>Manage chart favorites</title>
    <screenshot>
      <info><title>Data visualizer module displaying a column chart.</title></info>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="50%" fileref="resources/images/visualizer/chart_favorites.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <para>Saving your charts as favorites makes it easy to restore them later. It also gives you the
      opportunity to share them with other users as an interpretation or put it on the dashboard. </para>
    <section>
      <title>Save a chart as a favorite </title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis> dialog box opens.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Add new</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Create new favorite</emphasis> dialog box opens.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the text box, type the name you want to give your chart.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Create</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Open a favorite</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis> dialog box opens.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Find the favorite you want to open. You can either use <emphasis role="bold"
              >Prev</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Next</emphasis> or the search field to find
            a saved favorite. The list is filtered on every character that you enter.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click the name.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Rename a favorite</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis> dialog box opens.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Find the favorite you want to rename.</para>
          <para>You can either use <emphasis role="bold">Prev</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold"
              >Next</emphasis> or the search field to find a saved favorite. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click the grey rename icon next to the favorite's name.</para>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Rename favorite</emphasis> dialog box favorite
            opens.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Type the new name and click <emphasis role="bold">Update</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title><?oxy_comment_start author="Home" timestamp="20160412T140454+0200" comment="Revise title."?>Overwrite<?oxy_comment_end?>
        a favorite</title>
      <para>To save the current chart to an existing favorite (overwrite):</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis> dialog box opens.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Find the favorite you want to overwrite.</para>
          <para>You can either use <emphasis role="bold">Prev</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold"
              >Next</emphasis> or the search field to find a saved favorite. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click the green overwrite icon next to the favorite's name.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> to confirm that you want to overwrite the
            favorite.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="dvInterpretations">
      <title>Share a chart interpretation</title>
      <para role="">For
        <?oxy_comment_start author="Home" timestamp="20160407T151353+0200" comment="Which ones?"?>certain<?oxy_comment_end?>
        analysis-related resources in DHIS 2, you can share a data interpretation. An interpretation
        is a link to the relevant resource together with a text expressing some insight about the
        data. </para>
      <para role="">To create an interpretation of a map and share it with all users of the
        system:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open or create a favorite chart.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Share</emphasis> > <emphasis role="bold">Write
              interpretation</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Write interpretation</emphasis> dialog box opens.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the text field, type a comment, question or interpretation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Share</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>The dialog box closes automatically. You can see the interpretation on the <emphasis
              role="bold">Dashboard</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Modify sharing settings for a favorite</title>
      <para>After you have created a chart and saved it as a favorite, you can share the favorite
        with everyone or a user group. To modify the sharing settings:</para>
      <para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Find the favorite you want to share.</para>
            <para>You can either use <emphasis role="bold">Prev</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold"
                >Next</emphasis> or the search field to find a saved favorite.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para> Click the blue share icon next to the favorite's name.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>In the text box, enter the name of the user group you want to share your favorite
              with and click the <emphasis role="bold">+</emphasis> icon.</para>
            <para>The chosen user group is added to the list of recipients. </para>
            <para>Repeat the step to add more user groups. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If you want to allow external access, select the corresponding box.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>For each user group, choose an
              <?oxy_comment_start author="Home" timestamp="20160407T150433+0200" comment="Correct term?"?>access
              setting<?oxy_comment_end?>. The options are:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><?oxy_comment_start author="Home" timestamp="20160407T150510+0200" comment="Why is this option only available for Public access?"?>None<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Can view</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Can edit and view</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Delete a favorite</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Favorites</emphasis> dialog box opens.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Find the favorite you want to delete.</para>
          <para>You can either use <emphasis role="bold">Prev</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold"
              >Next</emphasis> or the search field to find a saved favorite. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click the red delete icon next to the favorite's name.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> to confirm that you want to delete the
            favorite.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dvEmbed">
    <title>Embed charts in any web page</title>
    <para>Certain analysis-related resources in DHIS 2, like pivot tables, charts and maps, can be
      embedded in any web page by using a plug-in. You will find more information about the plug-ins
      in the Web API chapter in the <emphasis>DHIS2 Developer Manual</emphasis>.</para>
    <para>To generate a HTML fragment that you can use to display the chart in an external web
      page:</para>
    <para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Share</emphasis> > <emphasis role="bold">Embed in web
              page</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Embed in web page</emphasis> window opens.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Select</emphasis> to highlight the HTML fragment.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Visualize a chart as a pivot table or a map</title>
    <para>When you have made a chart you can switch between pivot table, chart and map visualization
      of your data.
      <?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160421T155413+0200" comment="Verify with Jan."?>The
      function is inactive if the data the chart is based on cannot render as a pivot table or
      map.<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
    <section>
      <title>Open a chart as a pivot table</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Chart</emphasis> > <emphasis role="bold">Open this chart
              as table</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>Your current chart opens as a pivot table.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <screenshot>
        <info><title>Analysis
          <?oxy_comment_start author="CPersson" timestamp="20160421T155736+0200" comment="Consider removing screen shot.
If not, update it with new screenshot."?>integration<?oxy_comment_end?></title></info>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" scale="100"
              fileref="resources/images/visualizer/chart_integration.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Open a chart as a map</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Chart</emphasis> > <emphasis role="bold">Open this chart
              as map</emphasis>.</para>
          <para>Your current chart opens as a map.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>