<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Manage program validation rules</title>
    <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="180,215,3"?>
    <section>
        <title>Program validation rule</title>
        <para>To create validation rules for programs, click on the program which you would like and
            select <emphasis role="italic">Program validation rule management</emphasis> menu. Then
            click <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> button and enter values for the fields in
            form to create a new one. A validation rule is based on an expression which defines a
            relationship between data element values. The expression has a left side and a right
            side and an operator which defines whether the former must be less than, equal to or
            greater than the latter. The expression forms a condition which should assert that
            certain logical criteria are met. For instance, a validation rule could assert that an
            admitted date given is before the discharged date. </para>
    </section>
    <?oxy_custom_end?>
    <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="180,215,3"?>
    <section>
        <title>Validation criteria</title>
        <para>Validation criteria section provides a mechanism for defining criteria which validate
            if an entity can enrol into the program.</para>
        <para>To access the validation criteria maintenance module, click on the program which you
            would like and select <emphasis role="italic">View validation criteria</emphasis> link
            on context menu to open <emphasis role="italic">Validation criteria
                management</emphasis> form.</para>
        <para>To create a new validation criterion, click the <emphasis role="italic">Add
                new</emphasis> button. Fill all fields with read asterisk, and click <emphasis
                role="italic">Add</emphasis> button.</para>
        <para>To translate the name of a validate criteria, click on the program stage which you
            would like and select <emphasis role="italic">Translation</emphasis> link.</para>
    </section>
    <?oxy_custom_end?>
</section>
