<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>[Review ongoing] Manage custom registration forms</title>
    <section>
        <title>Tracked entity form</title>
        <para>The tracked entity form section provides a mechanism for defining custom registration
            form for each available program in system or for normal registration form which is used
            to register any entity without having program information and this entity can enroll
            into a certain program after that.</para>
        <para>To access the entity registration form maintenance module, from <emphasis
                role="italic">Apps</emphasis> menu, go to <emphasis role="italic">Programs /
                Attributes</emphasis> option and click on it and select <emphasis role="italic"
                >Tracked Entity Form</emphasis> option.</para>
        <para>To define a custom registration form, please select a program in list and click on the
            row corresponding the program you want to design. Then select <emphasis role="italic"
                >Design registration form</emphasis> link on context menu.</para>
        <note>
            <para>Check on<emphasis role="italic"> Auto save registration form</emphasis> checkbox
                in <emphasis role="italic">Design tracked entity form </emphasis>to save the custom
                registration form to being designed automatically.</para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>About program stage entry forms</title>
        <para>A program stage has three types of data entry forms:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Custom data entry form</emphasis> - Define a data
                    entry form as HTML page. click on the program stage which you would like and
                    select to define custom data entry form. The system supports to define a custom
                    entry form with multi stages. So this form can be re-used in other stages of the
                    same program.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Section data entry form</emphasis> - Group some data
                    elements which belong to the program stage as sections and display data elements
                    by each section. Click on the program stage which you would like and select
                        <emphasis role="italic">Section management</emphasis> link to define section
                    data entry form.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Default data entry form</emphasis> - List all data
                    elements which belong to the program stage.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Create a custom registration form</title>
        <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Create a custom program stage registration form</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Design data entry form</emphasis></para>
    </section>
</section>
    