<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>About push reports</title>
    <para>Push reports allows you to increase awareness and usage of data analysis by sending
        reports with charts, tables and maps directly to users e-mail addresses.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>A push report gets its content from existing dashboards.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>A push report lists the dashboard items in the same order as on the
                dashboard.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>A push report can only contain dashboard items with charts, maps or tables.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>You create the push report and its schedule in the <emphasis role="bold"
                    >Maintenance</emphasis> app.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Title</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold"
                    >Message</emphasis> parameters you set up in the <emphasis role="bold"
                    >Maintenance</emphasis> app, are included in each report. The <emphasis
                    role="bold">Name</emphasis> you give the report is not included in the report.
                Instead, the name is used to identify the push analysis object in the system. This
                way a report can be named one thing, and the title of the report can be
                another.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>When you run a push report job, the system compiles a list of recipients from the
                user groups you've selected. The system then generates a report for each member of
                the selected user groups. Each of the dashboard items are generated specifically for
                each user. This means that the data included in the report reflects the data the
                user has access to. All users could therefore get the same report (if all the data
                is "static") or custom reports (if all the data is "dynamic"), or a combination of
                the two.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Push reports are sent by e-mail to the recipients, not through the internal DHIS2
                messaging system. If a user doesn't have a valid e-mail, or if the job fails, no
                e-mails are sent. In this case, the problem is logged on the server.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <note>
        <para>The data generated in the push reports is public so verify that you don't include any
            sensitive data.</para>
    </note>
    <example>
        <title>Push report</title>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="80%" align="center"
                        fileref="resources/images/maintainence/push_report_ex.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
    </example>
    <para>In the <emphasis role="bold">Maintenance</emphasis> app, you manage the following push
        reports objects:</para>
    <table frame="all">
        <title>Push reports objects in the Maintenance app</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
            <thead>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Object type</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Available functions</para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Push analysis</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Create, edit, clone, delete, show details,
                            <?oxy_comment_start author="cecilia" timestamp="20160929T132146+0200" comment="Before release: Two more menu items have been added, pending info from SME." flag="done"?>translate<?oxy_comment_end?>,
                            preview and run</para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </table>
</section>
