<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xml:id="about_gis">
    <title>About the GIS app</title>
    <para>With the GIS app you can overlay multiple layers and choose among different base maps. You
        can create thematic maps of areas and points, view facilities based on classifications, and
        visualize catchment areas for each facility. You can add labels to areas and points, and
        search and filter using various criteria. You can move points and set locations on the fly.
        Maps can be saved as favorites and shared with other people.</para>
    <screenshot>
        <title>Here's an overview of the GIS app workspace</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="resources/images/gis/gis_main.png" align="center" width="90%"
                    format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>The icons in the top left corner represent the vector layers. They are the
                starting point of the <emphasis role="bold">GIS</emphasis> app.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>In the top right corner you get an overview of the layers:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The default base map is OSM Light. If you are online you will see a
                        detailed OpenStreetMap,
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="Home" timestamp="20160412T152838+0200" comment="Use of trademarks in documentaiton and interface must be reviewed.
https://www.google.com/permissions/trademark/trademark-list.html
"?>Google
                        Streets and Google Hybrid<?oxy_comment_end?> which can be used as background
                        maps and layers. Switch between the four of them by checking the check box.
                        By clearing a box you can hide the corresponding background
                        completely.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If you want to see the background, but with reduced opacity, you can set
                        the visibility to something lower than 100 % in the box to the right.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The panels below hold the map legends when you create a thematic map. A
                        legend explains the link between values and colors on your map.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Zoom to content</emphasis> automatically adjusts the zoom
                level and map center position to put the data on your map in focus.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To get information for an event, simply click it. This opens a pop-up window which
                displays all available information for that event.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Right-click to display the longitude and latitude of the map.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </section>
