<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>About the GIS app</title>
    <para>With the GIS app you can create thematic mapping of areas and points, view facilities
        based on classifications, and visualize catchment areas for each facility. You can define
        custom legend sets and link them to indicators, add labels to areas and points, and you can
        search and filter using various criteria. With the GIS app you can also overlay multiple
        layers and use Google Maps as a background layer. You can move points and set locations
        on-the-fly. Maps can be saved as favorites and shared with other people.</para>
    <screenshot>
        <?oxy_comment_start author="cecilia" timestamp="20160626T153414+0200" comment="Before release:
Replace screenshot."?>
        <title>Main GIS screen</title>
        <?oxy_comment_end?>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="resources/images/gis/gis_main.png" align="center" width="80%"
                    format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>The icons in the top left corner represent the vector layers and they are the
                starting point of the <emphasis role="bold">GIS</emphasis> app.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>In the top right corner you get an overview of the layers:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If you are online you will see
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="Home" timestamp="20160412T152838+0200" comment="Use of trademarks in documentaiton and interface must be reviewed.
https://www.google.com/permissions/trademark/trademark-list.html
"?>Google
                        Streets and Google Hybrid<?oxy_comment_end?> which can be used as background
                        maps and layers. Switch between the two of them by checking the check box.
                        The default base map is OpenStreetMap. To get a nice background map, select
                        the OSM Light. By clearing a box you can hide the corresponding background
                        completely.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If you want to see the background, but with reduced opacity, you can set
                        the visibility to something lower than 100 % in the box to the right.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The final four layers are the vector layers which you use for thematic
                        mapping (explained in the next section). The panels below hold the map
                        legends when you create a thematic map. A legend explains the link between
                        values and colors on your map.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Zoom to content</emphasis> automatically adjusts the zoom
                level and map center position to put the data on your map in focus.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To get information for an event you can simply click on it. This opens a pop-up
                window which displays all available information for that event.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The current longitude and latitude position of the mouse cursor is displayed in
                the bottom right corner of the map.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </section>
