<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="psi">
    <title>PSI: DHIS 2 as Management Information System</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">This interview was conducted in May 2016, with Sarah Romorini,
            Senior Program Manager at PSI. The aim of this interview was to find out more about how
            DHIS 2 has been rolled out and how it is being used by PSI today. Sarah Romorini has
            worked with PSI for the past ten years, most recently with the implementation of DHIS
            2.</emphasis></para>
    <section><title>About PSI</title><para>PSI is a global health organization dedicated to improving the health of people in the developing world by focusing on serious challenges like a lack of family planning, HIV and AIDS, barriers to maternal health, and the greatest threats to children under five, including malaria, diarrhea, pneumonia and malnutrition.</para><para>Founded in 1970, PSI provides lifesaving products, clinical services and behavior change communication that empower the world’s most vulnerable people to lead healthier lives. PSI works in partnership with local governments, ministries of health and local organizations to create health solutions that are built to last.</para><para>More than 8,900 staff work for PSI and its affiliates. Its world headquarters are in Washington, D.C. and its European offices are in Amsterdam. PSI works in more than 60 countries. In 2014, PSI’s revenue was calculated at $631,229,922 USD.</para></section>
    <section><title>Why did you choose DHIS 2 at PSI, what drove the decision?</title><para>In 2011, PSI began its search for a better Management Information System (MIS). Until then, we’d been using a different MIS in every country and even within countries, different MISs would be used for different projects. We were stuck with highly customized “boutique” systems – that is, unique data collection systems for every project. This was a mix of a Microsoft Excel, Access, and other tools. Programs were cobbling together pieces of information to see trends and analyze their programs. Accessing data like this wasn’t very efficient.</para><para>All of these unique, siloed systems led PSI to reflect upon two larger questions: how does PSI want to engage with its information, both locally and globally? And how do we want data to influence both the strategic and everyday program questions that PSI tackles?</para><para>During its search for a new, global MIS, several different systems were considered but in the end, DHIS2 was chosen for its ability to collect, manage, and visualize information…in essence, it was the system that made it easier for our programs to collect information and make decisions based off of data. It’s an incredibly powerful and flexible resource!</para><para>We were attracted to DHIS2’s ability to collect info on-the-go and the system’s ability to meet different needs. For example, users can set up their own entry forms, indicators and reports. DHIS2 is easily integrated with other interfaces; we especially liked that data collection and monitoring can be adapted for all program areas, including referrals, health services, sales and distribution.</para><para>Globally, PSI is making a huge push to make evidence-based decision-making easier for the
            field, and DHIS 2 is a very tangible tool in that sense. Capturing and analyzing
            real-time data for decision making is appealing and relevant for our field programs and
            organizationally, it reinforces how PSI’s programs are truly data-driven.</para>
        <para>
            <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref=".resources/images/use_cases/psi_cambodia_evidence_based_decision_making_workshop.jpg"
                            format="JPG" width="80%"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            <annotation>
                <para>PSI Cambodia participates in an evidence-based decision making workshop</para>
            </annotation>
        </para></section>
    <section><title>How did you roll out DHIS 2? Was it a gradual process, district by district for example? </title><para>No, we did it in true PSI fashion; we dived right in! We started with two pilot projects that were rolled out nationwide: one in Kenya and one in El Salvador. It was a huge benefit to have a low-complexity country like El Salvador and a high-complexity country like Kenya using DHIS 2.</para>
        <section><title>Kenya pilot project</title><para>Kenya was PSI’s largest pilot project for DHIS 2. All the projects are now reporting on DHIS 2. It was a very exciting process, as it was PSI’s first time implementing DHIS 2 at scale. In Kenya, there’s a wide range of programs on DHIS 2, including malaria, HIV, family planning, social franchising, hypertension, sales, cervical cancer, and others.</para></section>
        <section><title>El Salvador pilot project</title><para>In El Salvador, PSI’s reproductive health program was the first to join DHIS2. This helped
                monitor the effectiveness of interpersonal communication, quality assurance visits,
                provider performance, and helped the team identify trends and where to direct
                resources. I was a part of the El Salvador team at the time, and it was incredible
                to see how program managers and supervisors began using DHIS2 during meetings to
                illustrate trends, gaps, and program needs.</para>
            <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/images/use_cases/psi_scale.png" format="PNG"
                            width="90%" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot></section>
    </section>
    <section><title>How many PSI countries are using DHIS  2?</title><para>After setting up our two pilot projects, DHIS 2 grew very quickly at PSI…we created demand for this system and needed to meet other countries’ requests to introduce DHIS 2. From 2013 until now, PSI has over 20 countries reporting their data using DHIS 2 on the production server and several more are in development. Over 60 PSI countries use DHIS 2 to report their monthly aggregated health services data. With such a powerful tool, program managers can make better, data-driven decisions, which ultimately translates into improved programming.</para></section>
    <section><title>What are the differences between how PSI uses DHIS 2 and how the Ministries of Health do?</title><para>PSI and MoHs are using the same MIS, that is to say DHIS 2, but they are not using the same server. This means that the information on PSI’s DHIS 2 server and the information on the MoH’s DHIS 2 server are managed separately. Since PSI and the MoH capture different information, PSI’s is not creating a parallel system to the MoH. However, it enables the potential to share the information gathered by the other. In a few countries, MoHs have access to the information collected by PSI in their DHIS  2 server.</para></section>
    <section><title>How is DHIS 2 making changes to its programs and businesses?</title><para>DHIS 2 could be used as just another MIS for data collection, but fortunately it’s used for so much more. What we’re really interested in is seeing the programs using the information on DHIS 2 to influence their program decision making.</para><para>This is also part of a larger behavior change process to make better use of data and we’re
            asking ourselves:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How do we make sure that program managers are using this information to direct where resources should be better used?</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Who should we target to use information to drive changes within programs
                        and ensure that evidence-based decision-making is being applied?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para><para>DHIS 2 has enabled us to see how we’re performing in various areas of Behavior Change Communication (BCC). For example, we’ve better visibility on what our Interpersonal Communication (IPC) agents are doing. We can see the number of people that IPC agents have reached, the BCC activities that are taking place, and so forth.</para></section>
    <section><title>How do you implement DHIS 2? Do you use consultants or local PSI teams?</title>
        <section><title>Local PSI DHIS 2 stars</title><para>We’re working closely with PSI’s country teams so they feel empowered to use, manage, and analyze their data using DHIS 2. During DHIS 2 implementations, in-country DHIS 2 stars are identified and PSI provides coaching and assistance to empower them to integrate data for decision making—and DHIS 2!—into their every day program management.</para><para>We also identify local technical leads who can support DHIS 2 maintenance and adapt the system
                to meet their teams’ needs. For example, we’re implementing DHIS 2 in Zimbabwe and
                have an amazing MIS star there. Our team is working closely with him, and he’s
                learning how to build and do the configuration himself—and this includes some pretty
                complex integrations. It’s exciting to see how DHIS2 is really owned by PSI
                Zimbabwe—the data in DHIS 2 is theirs and they’re using it. This is the kind of goal
                we aspire to.</para>
            <para>
                <screenshot>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="resources/images/use_cases/psi_myanmar_maps_data_flow.jpg"
                                format="JPG" width="80%" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
                <annotation>
                    <para>PSI Myanmar maps out their data flow</para>
                </annotation>
            </para></section>
        <section><title>DHIS 2 Builders and Architects</title><para>Configuring DHIS 2 to meet a country’s data needs takes team work. To do this, PSI collaborates with “DHIS 2 builders,” who do the technical configuration work…that is, building the DHIS 2 system to match the DHIS 2 blueprint, which is based on the PSI country team’s data use needs.</para><para>These DHIS 2 builders are often HISP agencies in India, Vietnam, Uganda, West Africa, and
                Colombia. We also work with BAO Systems, the largest US-based DHIS 2 consulting and
                hosting firm in North America, for configuration support.<link
                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://baosystems.com/"
                /> As I mentioned before, we are also training PSI’s local DHIS 2 stars to lead configurations.</para><para>To make sure DHIS 2 configuration work meets PSI’s standards, DHIS 2 builders are supervised by PSI’s DHIS 2 Architects. The DHIS 2 Architects are an important part of our team and are specialized PSI DHIS 2 experts—they not only make sure PSI’s DHIS 2 configurations are high quality, but they also train local DHIS 2 stars and help DHIS 2 builders to learn PSI’s standards so our configurations become more efficient.</para></section>
    </section>
    <section><title>Do you provide DHIS 2 training to PSI staff?</title><para>As part of our long-term sustainability goals, we’re offering more training opportunities for local PSI staff on DHIS 2 administration and data use using DHIS 2, as well as for DHIS 2 builders so they familiarize themselves with PSI standards. Before, we would create these trainings a little on the fly because there were fewer countries, but now we’re starting to create more standard, ready-to-go training resources. This helps us to save time and improve our curriculum based off of experience—this is also part of our strategy to reach scale.</para><para>We also send PSI staff to the introductory and advanced trainings that HISPs offer.</para></section>
    <section><title>Which parts of DHIS 2 are you using the most?</title><para>Probably the aggregate data forms. But I’d like to see PSI using Tracker even more….it’s an incredibly flexible tool! More and more countries are using the DHIS 2 tracking feature. You can look at individual data, register individual cases, track individual cases and then conduct surveys. This means that you can capture detailed information and then analyze this information, to get the bigger picture about what’s going on. </para><para>Within PSI, we have a large network of franchised clinics and there are ongoing discussions about the direction we want to take with electronic medical records and Clinic Management Information Systems. So…whatever solution we’re proposing needs to be DHIS-2 compatible. Now we’re at the point where we’re asking ourselves: What’s DHIS 2’s limit? </para></section>
    <section><title>How do you go about customizing DHIS 2? </title><para>Right now we’re focusing on strengthening how we implement DHIS 2 and the process we use. We’re identifying what needs to happen and when, and the information we need to understand how the PSI country team will use DHIS 2. Each country has its unique configuration, but there are core business processes that remain the same. So we’re identifying how this connects to the information that we need to see and the decisions that we need to make. </para></section>
    <section><title>What’s the general feedback you get on DHIS 2?</title><para>It’s an incredibly powerful tool, but it’s not necessarily intuitive to create your own form or how you create your own dashboard. Sometimes that can be a barrier for PSI country teams to make full use of DHIS 2. We’re looking to make that easier, and we’re identifying who really needs to be able to do what with DHIS 2. For example, does a senior manager really need to create her own dashboard, or is it OK that someone else does it for her, if she can access and see her dashboards? Based off of this, we can understand who needs to be trained on what. </para></section>
    <section><title>How do you help DHIS 2 users with the system?</title><para>We’ve recently transitioned to BAO Systems to help PSI to field its Help Desk tickets. For example, if a user gets stuck with a dashboard query, they submit a ticket through the Help Desk, which is mainly answered by BAO, with support from PSI’s DHIS 2 Architects. We try to have a local DHIS 2 administrator in each PSI country we work in; this person can usually field basic questions, like how to reset a password, or intermediate ones, like how to create a new form. Questions in the Help Desk range from basic to advanced, like reporting a bug, which may need to be sent to Oslo.</para></section>
    <section><title>Do you embed DHIS 2 into other apps?</title><para>Absolutely! In addition to using DHIS 2 as our MIS, PSI develops custom reports and apps to make real time data collection and analysis even easier. Different apps address key strategic and technical areas, including franchise management and provider performance, improving network quality, and case surveillance (such as malaria). All the information collected via apps is directly pushed into DHIS 2. Analytics are automatically updated, giving users real-time information and visual analytics that makes data-driven decision making easier. </para>
        <section><title>Health Network Quality Improvement System (HNQIS) app</title><para>The HNQIS app was developed by PSI with the aim to improve network quality and provider
                performance. It’s an impressive app that responds to a very real program need: How
                do we improve the quality of care that providers deliver more effectively? It helps
                Quality Assurance (QA) officers plan their supervision routes and target
                low-performing providers with high client volume. QA officers use PSI- and
                MoH-approved checklists in the app to conduct assessments with PSI’s providers. QA
                officers can easily monitor trends in network quality and identify how best to
                allocate their time and resources to improve their providers’ performance. This app
                can be used both on and offline.</para>
            <para>
                <screenshot>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="resources/images/use_cases/hnqis_app_used_glory_clinic_nairobi_kenya.jpg"
                                format="JGP" width="80%" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
                <annotation>
                    <para>HNQIS app being used in Glory Clinic in Nairobi, Kenya</para>
                </annotation>
            </para></section>
        <section><title>Malaria case surveillance mobile app </title><para>This is a really simple and elegant app and has a lot of potential—it’s being used in Cambodia
                to quickly report positive malaria cases in almost real time. It’s super intuitive,
                so anyone who can use a smartphone can use it. Pharmacists and other health
                providers use this app to collect basic data points - like geographic location, type
                of malaria detected and age/gender of the client. This information helps PSI and our
                partners to track malaria cases, identify outbreaks and re-direct resources to where
                they are most needed. Check it out—it’s on Google Play.</para>
            <para>
                <screenshot>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="resources/images/use_cases/pharmacist_cambodia_uses_malaria_case_surveillance_app.png"
                                align="center" format="PNG" width="90%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
                <annotation>
                    <para>A pharmacist in Cambodia uses the Malaria Case Surveillance app</para>
                </annotation>
            </para></section>
    </section></chapter>
