<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Feature
        <?oxy_comment_start author="cecilia" timestamp="20160915T115120+0200" comment="Add links to acronyms, styleguide wiki"?>name<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
    <para> [Provide the feature name here.]</para>
    <section>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">This section answers the question “What is this
                feature?”</emphasis></para>
        <para> [Enter an overview of the feature as you would explain it to a technical writer —
            what is this feature all about?</para>
        <para>[Provide essential background information that users must understand before they can
            complete the tasks successfully.]</para>
        <para>[Insert a workflow if applicable]</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Reason</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">This section answers the question “Why do I need this
                feature?”</emphasis></para>
        <para>[A feature is usually implemented to solve a business issue. Explain this issue to the
            user here.]</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Tasks</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">This section answers the question “How do I use this
                feature?”</emphasis></para>
        <para>[Provide a detailed procedure for running the feature. The procedure should have
            multiple steps on how to achieve the goal. Include screenshots as needed. Make sure you
            are not including any confidential data in the screenshots.</para>
        <para>[Tasks are the main building blocks for task-oriented user documentation. They provide
            step-by-step instructions that lets the user perform a task.]</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Reference information</title>
        <para>[Provide this information if applicable.]</para>
        <para>[A reference topic documents programming constructs or facts about a product. Examples
            of reference information are: language elements, class descriptions, commands,
            functions, statements, protocols, types, declarators, operands, and API
            information.</para>
        <para>[Reference information provides quick access to facts, but no explanation of concepts
            or procedures. Assume that users already understand the base technology.</para>
        <para>[Reference information is usually included in a table to allow the user to scan
            through the information quickly and easily.]</para>
    </section>
</section>
