<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Setting up Data Quality functionality</title>
  <para>The data quality module provides means to improve the quality of the data in the system. This can be done through validation rules and various statistical checks.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Overview of data quality check</title>
    <para>Ensuring data quality is a key concern in building an effective HMIS. Data quality has different dimensions including:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Correctness:</emphasis> Data should be within the normal range for data collected at that facility. There should be no gross discrepancies when compared with data from related data elements.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Completeness:</emphasis> Data for all data elements for all health facilities/blocks/Taluka/districts should have been submitted.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Consistency:</emphasis> Data should be consistent with data entered during earlier months and years while allowing for changes with reorganization, increased work load, etc. and consistent with other similar facilities.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Timeliness:</emphasis> All data from all health facilities/blocks/Taluka/districts should be submitted at the appointed time.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Data quality checks</title>
    <para>Data quality checking can be done through various means, including:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>At point of data entry, the software can check the data entered to see if it falls within the min-max ranges of that data element (based on all previous data registered).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Defining various validation rules, which can be run once the user has finished data entry. The user can also check the entered data for a particular period and Organization Unit(s) against the validation rules, and display the violations for these validation rules. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Analysis of data sets, i.e. examining gaps in data.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data triangulation which is comparing the same data or indicator from different sources.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Data quality check at the point of data entry </title>
    <para>Data quality can be checked at the point of data entry through setting the minimum and maximum value range for each element manually or generating a range (defined by a minimum and maximum value). The min-max range can be generated automatically by the system. The auto-generated min-max range is suitable only for normally distributed data. DHIS2 will determine the arithmetic mean and standard deviation of all values for a given  data element /category option / organisation unit combination. Then the system will calculate the min-max range based on the </para>
    <para>For data which is highly-skewed or zero inflated (as is often the case with aggregate data), the values which DHIS2 may not provide an accurate min-max range, which may then result in excessive false violations. Also note that currently, min-max values are calculated across all attribute combo options for a given data element /category option / organisation unit combination. In summary, the automatic generation of min/max values can be useful for many situations, but it would be advised to ensure that the data is actually normally distributed prior to using this function. </para>
    <section>
      <title>Setting the minimum and maximum value range manually </title>
      <para>If you are using the default entry screen click on the element for which you want to set the min-max value. A pop-up window will appear in which you can enter the values. On subsequent data entry, if the values entered do not fall within the min-max range,  the data entry cell will appear with an orange background, to highlight that this value does not fall within the min-max range. The min-max limits can be set in the following dialog. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="resources/images/data_quality/set_min_max_manually.png" format="PNG" width="30%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>In the same screen , users can comment on the reason for the discrepancy, such as an event at a facility which may have generated a large number of clients. Users may also flag the value for follow up (by pressing the star). </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Generated min-max values </title>
      <para>It is possible to generate and remove the min-max ranges by dataset using the &quot;Min-max generation&quot; function available in the data administration module. Just select a dataset and then an organisation unit from the dialog, as shown below. </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" width="40%" fileref="resources/images/data_quality/generate_min_max.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <para>Pressing &quot;Generate&quot; will create new min/max ranges for all data elements in the selected data sets for all orgunits (including descendants) of the selected organisation units.</para>
      <para>Pressing &quot;Remove&quot; will permanently delete all min/max ranges for the selected datasetsa and organisation units.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="validationRule">
    <title>Validation Rule</title>
    <para>This module provides management of validation rules. A validation rule is based on an expression which defines a relationship between a number of data elements. The expression has a left side, a right side and an operator which defines whether the former must be less than, equal to or greater than the latter. The expression forms a condition which should assert that certain logical criteria are met. For instance, a validation rule could assert that the total number of vaccines given to infants is less than or equal to the total number of infants.</para>
    <para>To add a validation rule, just follow these steps from the Data Quality -&gt; Validation Rule dialog:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click on the <emphasis role="italic">Add new</emphasis> button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Provide a descriptive <emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis> for the validation rule. The name must be unique among the validation rules.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Provide a <emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis> for the validation rule.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the <emphasis role="italic">Importance</emphasis> you wish to assign to the validation rule: <emphasis role="italic">high</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">medium</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic">low</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the <emphasis role="italic">Rule type</emphasis>. For validating correct data, choose <emphasis role="italic">Validation</emphasis>. For monitoring  data according to a rule, choose <emphasis role="italic">Surveillance</emphasis> and follow the extra instructions below.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the <emphasis role="italic">Period type</emphasis> for the data being validated.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select an <emphasis role="italic">Operator</emphasis>. The operator options are <emphasis role="italic">equal</emphasis> (==), <emphasis role="italic">not equal</emphasis> (!=), <emphasis role="italic">greater than</emphasis> (&gt;), <emphasis role="italic">greater than or equal</emphasis> (&gt;=), <emphasis role="italic">less than</emphasis> (&lt;), <emphasis role="italic">less than or equal to</emphasis> (&gt;=), a <emphasis role="italic">compulsory pair</emphasis> or an <emphasis>exclusive pair</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>The compulsory pair operator allows you to require that data values must be entered for a form for both left and right sides of the expression, or for neither side. In other words, you can require that if one field in a form is filled, then one or more other fields must also be filled.</para>
        <para>The exclusive pair operator allows you to assert that if any value exist on the left side then there should be no values on the right side (or vice versa). Stated another way, this means that data elements which compose the rule on either side should be mutually exclusive from each other, for a given  time period / organisation unit /attribute option combo. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Define the <emphasis role="italic">left side</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">right side</emphasis> of the validation rule expression. First, provide a description for the expression. Second, build the expression with the expression builder. The expression is mathematical and contain data elements as well as integers and mathematical operators. Data elements can be included by double-clicking one in the available data elements list to the right. Alternatively one can select a data element and click the insert button. Mathematical operators can be included by clicking the corresponding button under the expression builder area.</para>
        <para>There are three states which can be set to alter how the validation rule will be evaluated if there is any missing data. </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Skip if any value is missing: The rule will be skipped if any of the values which compose the expression are missing. This is the default option.  This option should always be selected if you are using the &quot;Exclusive&quot; or &quot;Compulsory&quot; pair operator.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Skip if all values are missing: The rule will be skipped only if all of the operands which compose it are missing. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Never skip: The rule will never be skipped in case of missing data, and all missing operands will be treated effectively as a zero.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Save each expression by clicking <emphasis role="italic">Save</emphasis>, then save the validation rule by clicking <emphasis role="italic">Save</emphasis>.</para>
    <para>To edit a validation rule, click the name the relevant validation rule in the list  and select &quot;Edit&quot; from the context menu. Then follow the same procedures as above when creating a new rule.</para>
    <para>To delete a validation rule, click the name of the validation rule to be deleted, and select &quot;Remove&quot; from the context menu.</para>
    <para>Validation rule names can be translated to other languages by selecting the name of the validation rule and selecting &quot;Translate&quot; from the context menu. </para>
    <para>To view validation rule details, click the name of the validation rule, and then select &quot;Show details&quot; from the context menu. </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="validationRuleGroup">
    <title>Validation Rule Group</title>
    <para>A validation rule group provides a mechanism for classifying related validation rules. Another advantage of using validation rule groups is that it can later be run separately, instead of running all validation rules.</para>
    <para>You can run the validation rules in a group interactively. To do so, choose Data Quality -&gt; Validation Rule. You can choose whether to run all validation rules in the system, or just the rules in one group.</para>
    <para>You can also run the rules in a group as part of a scheduled validation run, as described below.</para>
    <para>For each validation rule group, you can specify one or more groups of users to be notified of validation rule exceptions. Alerts will be sent to these users from scheduled validation runs, or from interactive runs when you request to send alerts. To set this up:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
<?dbfo keep-together="always" ?>      <listitem>
        <para>Be sure that one or more user groups contain all the users you wish to notify.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Define a validation rule group for a set of validation rules. In the section User groups to alert, select one or more user groups to be notified.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>By repeating these two steps, you can build any set of relations you need between validation rules and users to notify.</para>
    <para>When you create or edit a validation rule group, there is an option called <emphasis role="italic">Only organisation unit related users are alerted</emphasis>. If this is set to <emphasis role="italic">Yes</emphasis>, then each user in the user group(s) will be alerted only for validation exceptions in an organisation unit to which the user has been assigned through user management -- or for any lower-level organisation unit under the assigned organisation unit. If this is set to <emphasis role="italic">No</emphasis>, then each user in the assigned user group(s) will be alerted for all validation exceptions in the group, regardless of their user-assigned organisation units.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ScheduledValitionRuns">
    <title>Scheduled Validation Runs</title>
    <para>To enable routine scheduling of data validation runs, choose Data Administration from the Maintenance menu. Then click on Scheduling. If scheduling is active, click on the Stop button. Then select the Data monitoring strategy of All daily. Finally enable scheduling by clicking on the Start button.</para>
    <para>During a scheduled validation run, those validation rule groups will be evaluated that have one or more user groups defined for alerts. Validation rule groups that have no user groups defined for alerts will not be run during a scheduled run.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
