<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section version="5.0"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xml:id="manage_attributes">
    <title>Surveillance
        <?oxy_comment_start author="cecilia" timestamp="20161007T174156+0200" comment="Obsolete material from 2.25
Some content could be used for Predictors."?>Rules<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
    <section>
        <title>Surveillance Rules</title>
        <para>As well as checking for correct data, you can use a validation rules to find
            unexpected data values when compared with data from previous time periods. These kinds
            of validation rules are called <emphasis role="italic">surveillance</emphasis> rules. In
            surveillance rules, the right and left side expressions can include statistical
            functions (such as AVG or STDDEV) of samples derived from data elements in past periods
            for a particular organization level.</para>
        <para>Statistical functions in surveillance rules operate over samples generated by
            evaluating expressions in past periods. Surveillance rules can either generate samples
            around the same period in multiple years (seasonal rules) or across periods preceding
            the current one (serial rules). The generated samples are based on an <emphasis>annual
                sample count</emphasis> (<emphasis role="italic">nyears</emphasis>), a
                <emphasis>sequential sample count</emphasis> (<emphasis role="italic"
                >nperiods</emphasis>) and a <emphasis>sequential skip count</emphasis> (<emphasis
                role="italic">skipcount</emphasis>). For serial rules, <emphasis role="italic"
                >nperiods</emphasis> periods are sampled, excluding the immediately preceding
                <emphasis role="italic">skipcount</emphasis> periods. For seasonal rules, the sample
            periods include these samples (from the current year) as well as a window of <emphasis
                role="italic">2*nperiods+1</emphasis> periods around the corresponding year in each
            of the <emphasis role="italic">nyears</emphasis> past years. Any periods within
            skipcount of the current period are excluded. For example, suppose a monthly seasonal
            surveillance rule had an annual sample count of 3 (years), a sequential sample count of
            2 (months), and a skip count of 1 (month). There would be up to 16 samples including one
            from the current year (the month before last) and 15 samples based on a window of 5
            monthly samples (around the current month) in each of 3 preceding years. Note that if
            surveillance rules operate over a large number of samples, their execution may take
            substantial time and system resources.</para>
        <para>To add a surveillance rule, follow the steps above for validation rules, choosing a
                <emphasis role="italic">
                <emphasis role="italic">rule type</emphasis>
            </emphasis> of <emphasis role="italic">Surveillance</emphasis>. This adds the following
            validation rule options:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Choose an <emphasis role="italic">Organisation unit level</emphasis> for this
                    surveillance rule. If the data you wish to monitor is not entered at this level,
                    it will be aggregated from lower level organisation units in the organisation
                    unit hierarchy.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Enter the <emphasis role="italic">Sequential sample count</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Enter the <emphasis role="italic">Annual sample count</emphasis>.</para>
                <para>The sequential sample count <emphasis role="italic">or</emphasis> annual
                    sample count must be at least 1.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Enter the <emphasis role="italic">Sequential skip count</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>A surveillance rule may contain data elements for periods that are longer than the
            period given for the rule. This is useful, for example, if you want to divide a data
            element value by the population count, and the population count is entered annually. The
            data for the longer period type (e.g. population count) must be entered for a period
            that overlaps with the start of the period being evaluated. For example, if the period
            being evaluated is the week starting January 6, 2014, the yearly population count must
            be entered for the year containing January 6 2014. If the data element is from a longer
            period type than the rule period type, it must have an aggregation operator of average,
            not sum. In other words, only data elements that don&apos;t sum through time (like
            population count) can be used from longer periods than the rule period.</para>
        <para>The statistical functions available to surveillance rules are:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>AVG</emphasis> returns the arithmetic mean (average) of the sample
                    values.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>COUNT</emphasis> returns the number of sample values.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>STDDEV</emphasis> returns the standard deviation of the sample
                    values against the average.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>MEDIAN</emphasis> returns the median of the samples</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>MAX</emphasis> returns the maximum value among the samples</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>MIN</emphasis> returns the minimum value among the samples</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>VSUM</emphasis> returns the sum of all the sample values</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For surveillance rules, the <emphasis role="italic">skip for missing</emphasis> option
            has additional meaning. For past periods, absent data values for a period will lead to a
            missing sample point, rather than skipping the entire rule. The statistical functions
            will then operate over the available samples. Also, when values are being aggregated
            from lower levels of the organisation unit hierarchy, <emphasis role="italic">skip for
                missing</emphasis> skips the rule (or the sample point) when values are unavailable
                <emphasis>for</emphasis> any of the organisational subunits.</para>
    </section>
</section>
